Dr. rer. nat. Martin Bies

Curriculum Vitae



RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau
Department of Mathematics
Gottlieb-Daimler-Straße 48 (Office 433)
67663 Kaiserslautern, Germany
December 15, 1987 (Merzig, Germany)
Single (Not Married)
+49 (0)631 205 2850
bies@mathematik.uni-kl.de
https://martinbies.github.io/

German
Native
English
Full Proficiency
French
Modest (CEFR Level B1)

SUMMARY

I hold a **PhD** in **Physics** (*Heidelberg Univ., 2018*), specializing in string theory and mathematics. My research is inspired by computational analysis of massless spectra in string vacua, resulting in publications on toric geometry, Freyd categories, Brill-Noether theory, and root bundles. Proficient in *julia*, C++, and *python*, I excel in open-source software development (*git*) to advance computational research. My diverse expertise emphasizes my interdisciplinary commitment. With a history of international collaborations, full English proficiency, and extensive teaching experience, I showcase a versatile skill set.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

CURRENT, FROM IO/2022 (FT)

Mathematics Dept., RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, GER *Research Associate*

I enhance the toric geometry capabilities and develop advanced algebraic geometry tools for string theory geometries within the OSCAR computer algebra system (oscar-system.org). Funded by the SFB-TRR 195 – Symbolic Tools in Mathematics and their Application, I added/modified 142,000+ lines of code.

09/202I - 08/2022 (FT)

Dept. of Phys. & Astron., University of Pennsylvania, USA *Simons Postdoctoral Fellow*

Continuation of Simons Foundation project.

09/2020 - 08/202I (FT)

Dept. of Mathematics, University of Pennsylvania, USA **Simons Postdoctoral Fellow**

Work with M. Cvetič and R. Donagi on root bundles and the F-theory QSMs (funded by the Simons Foundation).

10/2019 - 09/2020 (FT)

Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, UK *Long Term Visitor*

Continuation of Wiener-Anspach project initiated at PTM, Brussels.

10/2018 - 09/2019 (FT)

PTM, Université Libre de Bruxelles, BE

Postdoctoral Researcher

M/F-Theory: Engineering Of Super Conformal Field Theories (funded by the *Foundation Wiener-Anspach*).

02/2018 - 09/2018 (FT)

ITP, Heidelberg University, GER

Research Associate

AI-tools meet jumps in vector-like spectra (preparation of Cluster of Excellence EXC 2181 STRUCTURES).

EDUCATION

03/2014 - 02/2018 PhD in Physics (Grade: Magna Cum Laude)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND (PHYSICS) & PROF. M. BARAKAT (MATHEMATICS)

Heidelberg University, GER

09/2012 - 02/2014 Master of Physics (Grade: 1.0)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND Heidelberg University, GER

10/2010 - 06/2011 **ERASMUS** exchange student

Imperial College, London

10/2008 - 08/2012 **Bachelor of Physics (Grade: 1.1)**

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND Heidelberg University, GER

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

04/2024 - CURRENT TU-Nachwuchsring

Funding: 3000€.

Status: M. Mikelsons (BSc. Mathematics) hired as research assistant.

Goal: Improve FTheoryTools and exploit this software tool for research paper.

01/2010 - 02/2018 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes

2014: Awarded PhD scholarship. 2010: Awarded Master scholarship.

CURRENT COLLABORATIONS

FROM 2022 FTheoryTools in OSCAR

Initiated with **A. P. Turner** (*University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Later joined by M. Zach (RPTU KL-LD, GER), Prof. Frühbis-Krüger (Univ. Oldenburg, GER).

Goal: In OSCAR, create computer tools for F-theory applications.

Key features: Crepant singularity resolution and database of existing constructions.

Status: First paper expected by mid-2024, paving way for cutting-edge applications.

From 04/2024: Research Assistant M. Mikelisons (funded by *TU-Nachwuchsring*).

FROM 2021 Toric Geometry in OSCAR

Together with **L. Kastner** (Technische Universitaet Berlin, GER) and support by the OSCAR team.

Goal: Solid foundation of toric geometry in OSCAR and integration with Polymake.

Status: **S. Telen**'s (MPI-MiS Leipzig, GER) lecture used OSCAR's toric geometry: arxiv-2203.01690.

An overview over the available functionality has been given in publication #10 (Mar. 2023).

G. Muratore's (Univ. de Lisboa, PRT) article arxiv-2309.03741 is based on our work.

A dedicated OSCAR book chapter will detail further updates, due in 2024.

FROM 2020 Applications of Root Bundles to F-theory Standard Models

Collaboration with **Prof. M. Cvetič** and **Prof. R. Donagi** (*University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Initially, contributions from **M. Liu** (back then, PhD student at *University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Continued work with **M. Ong** (PhD student at *University of Pennsylvania, USA*). Goal: Explore creating a single Higgs field in F-theory standard models using root bundles. Status: Resulted in 4 peer-reviewed papers (#1, 2, 3, 4) and preprint #9 from Jul. 2023.

SERVICES

07/2024	Organizing session at conference ICMS 2024 (together with M. Zach & L. Kastner).
02/2024	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board – virtual event via zoom.
FALL 2023	Expert at European Commission: Accessment of research proposals in Mathematics and Physics.
SINCE 202I	10+ letters of recommendation.
06/2018	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Heidelberg.
12/2017	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Ellwangen III.
05/2017	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Training for admission board members – successfully completed.
11/2016	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Heidelberg.

OTHER TRAININGS

03/2024	Moderation of meetings and project discussions (Kaiserslautern, GER). Offered by: <i>TU Nachwuchsring</i>
05/2018	Kontaktseminar – Schwerpunkt Banken und Beratung (Bonn, GER) Offered by: Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes
05/2018	Physiker im Beruf (Bad Honnef, GER) Offered by: Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft (DPG)

PUBLICATIONS

```
0000-0002-9609-1693
                  ORCID
                          57197835420
                 SCOPUS
                           5 (Based on peer-reviewed works, only.)
                H-INDEX
    TOTAL PUBLICATIONS
PEER REVIEWED/ACCEPTED
          UNDER REVIEW
              OUTREACH
           UNPUBLISHED
                  THESIS
              JOUR NALS
                          Journal of High Energy Physics (5)
                          Journal of Algebra and Its Applications (1)
                           Physical Review D (1)
                           Proceedings of Symposia in Pure Mathematics (AMS) (1)
```

Peer Reviewed Publications

- M. Bies, Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models, in String-Math 2022, R. Donagi, A. Langer, P. Sułkowski, and K. Wendland, eds., Proceedings of Symposia in Pure Mathematics, vol. 107, American Mathematical Society, 2024, pp. 17–43. ISBN: 978-1-4704-7240-5. DOI: 10.1090/pspum/107. (A preprint is available at arXiv:2303.08144.)
- 2 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, Brill-Noether-general Limit Root Bundles: Absence of vector-like Exotics in F-theory Standard Models, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2022, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP11(2022)004.
- 3 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, M. Liu, Statistics of Root Bundles Relevant for Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs, Physical Review D, Sept. 2021, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.104.L061903.
- 4 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Liu, M. Ong, Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs, Journal of High Energy Physics, Sept. 2021, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP09(2021)076
- 5 M. Bies, S. Posur, *Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors*, Journal of Algebra and Its Applications, July. 2021, DOI: 10.1142/s0219498822501869.
- 6 **M. Bies**, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, L. Ling, M. Liu, F. Ruehle, *Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, Jan. 2021, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP01(2021)196.
- 7 M. Bies, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, Algebraic Cycles and Local Anomalies in F-theory, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2017, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)100.
- 8 **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, *Gauge Backgrounds and Zero-Mode Counting in F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2017, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)081.

Preprints currently under Review

9 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, *Improved Statistics for F-theory Standard Models*, Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02535, Jul. 2023, under review at *Communications in Mathematical Physics*.

Outreach

- M. Bies, A. P. Turner, *F-Theory Applications*, in *The Computer Algebra System OSCAR: Algorithms and Examples*, W. Decker, C. Eder, C. Fieker, M. Horn, and M. Joswig, eds., Algorithms and Computation in Mathematics, vol. 32, Springer, 1st ed., August 2024, pp. 453–475. ISSN: 1431-1550.
- M. Bies, L. Kastner, *Toric Geometry*, in *The Computer Algebra System OSCAR: Algorithms and Examples*, W. Decker, C. Eder, C. Fieker, M. Horn, and M. Joswig, eds., Algorithms and Computation in Mathematics, vol. 32, Springer, 1st ed., August 2024, pp. 193–213. ISSN: 1431-1550.
- M. Bies, L. Kastner, *Toric Geometry in OSCAR*, ComputerAlgebraRundbrief 72 (03/2023), 20-25, Mar. 2023, Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08110.

Unpublished Works

13 **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, C. Pehle, T. Weigand, *Chow Groups, Deligne Cohomology and Massless Matter in F-theory*, Feb. 2014, https://arxiv.org/abs/1402.5144.

Thesis

- M. Bies, Cohomologies of Coherent Sheaves and Massless Spectra in F-theory, PhD thesis, Heidelberg university, Feb. 2018, Heidelberg University Library, available at DOI: 10.11588/HEIDOK.00024045.
- 15 **M. Bies**, Cohomologies of holomorphic line bundles in smooth and compact normal toric varieties, MSc. thesis, Heidelberg university, February 2014, available on author's academic homepage.
- 16 **M. Bies**, Intersecting D6-brane models on $T^2 \times T^2 \times T^2 / (\sigma \times \Omega)$ and $T^2 \times T^2 \times T^2 / (\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2 \times \sigma \times \Omega)$ orientifolds, BSc. thesis, Heidelberg university, August 2012, available on author's academic homepage.

TALKS, POSTERS, CONFERENCES

Invited Tal	ks (8)
07/2023	Third Annual Meeting 2023 of SFB-TRR 195 (Saarbruecken, GER) Title: F-Theory: Exemplifying OSCAR's Pursuit for Multidisciplinary Excellence
05/2023	Oberseminar algebraische Geometrie (Saarbruecken, GER) Title: F-Theory and Singular Elliptic Fibrations
10/2020	Philadelphia, USA Title: Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory
06/2020	Summer Series on String Phenomenology (Virtual) Title: On Stratification Diagrams, Algorithmic Spectrum Estimates and Vector-Like Pairs in F-theory
12/2019	Philadelphia, USA Title: From F-theory Standard Models to Freyd Categories and back
10/2018	Brussels, BE Title: Counting Massless Matter in F-theory with CAP
08/2018	CAP_days 2018 (Siegen, GER) Title: CAP, Machine Learning and String Theory
07/2014	Aachen, GER Title: The Standard Model from String Theory
Other Talk	s at Conferences, Workshops etc. (14)
07/2023	StringMath 2023 (Melbourne, AU) Title: Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models
07/2023	StringPheno 2023 (Daejeon, KR) Title: Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models
05/2023	Computeralgebra Tagung 2023 (Hannover, GER) Title: F-Theory Tools: String theory Applications of OCSAR
07/2022	String Math 2022 (Warsaw, PL) Title: Towards F-theory MSSMs
07/2022	String Pheno 2022 (Liverpool, UK) Title: Towards F-theory MSSMs
09/2021	Summer Series on String Phenomenology (virtual meeting) Title: Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs
12/2020	String Data 2020 (virtual conference) Title: Vector-like spectra in F-theory (joined with M. Liu)
08/2019	Gap Singular Meeting and School (Lambrecht, GER) Title: Monoidal Structures in Freyd Categories
05/2018	Seminar on <i>Holography and Large-N duality</i> (Heidelberg, GER) Title: Conformal Invariants; Fefferman–Graham Expansion; Graham–Lee Theorem (with M. Zikidis
07/2017	String Pheno 2017 (Virginia, USA) Title: Zero Mode Counting in F-Theory via CAP
08/2014	GAP Days (Aachen, GER) Title: String Theory, Sheaf Cohomology and the homal & Package

```
05/2014
           Seminar Series What is? (Heidelberg, GER)
           Title: What is a Fermion/Boson (in Quantum Mechanics)?
           Heidelberg, GER
 02/2014
           Title: Cohomology of Holomorphic Pullback Line Bundles on Smooth, Compact Normal Toric Varieties
           Heidelberg, GER
 05/2012
           Title: Intersecting D6-Brane Models
Posters at Conferences, Workshops etc. (2)
           StringMath 2023 (Melbourne, AU)
 07/2023
           Title: FTheoryTools – A Computer Tool for Singular Elliptic Fibrations
           Strings and Geometry (Oxford, UK)
 09/2019
           Title: Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors
Conferences attended without Talk or Poster Contribution (17)
 07/2022
           Strings 2022 (Vienna, AT)
           Simons Collab.: Geometry, Topology and Singular Special Holonomy Spaces (Freiburg, GER)
 06/2022
           Simons Collab. (Homological Mirror Symmetry) Annual Meeting (New York, USA)
  11/2021
           Simons Collab.: Progress and Open Problems (Stony Brook, USA)
 09/2021
           Simons Collab. (Special Holonomy in Geometry, Analysis, Phys.) Annual Meeting (New York, USA)
 09/2021
 07/2021
           String Pheno 2021 (virtual conference)
 06/2021
          Strings 2021 (virtual conference)
 06/2021
           String Math 2021 (virtual conference)
          String Pheno 2020 (virtual conference)
 06/2020
           Strings 2019 (Brussels, BE)
 07/2019
  03/2018
           String Data 2018 (Munich, GER)
          String Math 2015 (Sanya, CN)
  12/2015
  09/2015
           Third GAP Days (Trondheim, NO)
           Second GAP Days (Aachen, GER)
  03/2015
           Physics and Geometry of F-Theory (Munich, GER)
  02/2015
           Homological Perturbation Theory (Galway, IE)
  12/2014
           Geometry and Physics of String Compactifications (Heidelberg, GER)
 02/2014
```

TEACHING RECORD

Autonomous Instruction of Lecture Courses

Period	Title	University	Students	Weekly Teaching	Evaluation
04/2024 - 07/2024	Introduction to Topology	RPTU KL-LD, GER	_	$1 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$	_
01/2022 - 05/2022	Computational Linear Algebra	University Of Pennsylvania, USA	29	$2 \times 1.5 \text{hours}$	2.12
01/2021 – 05/2021	Computational Linear Algebra	University Of Pennsylvania, USA	57	$2 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$	2.04
	C = 1 D / V = 1 D V =	. / \ 0 1/ \ 77	1/\	11 / \	

Scale: Poor (o), Fair (1), Good (2), Very good (3), Excellent (4).

Senior Teaching Assistant

Period	Title	University	Students	Weekly Teaching
10/2023 – current	Algebraic Geometry	RPTU KL-LD, GER	6	$1 \times 1.5 \mathrm{hours}$
04/2018 – 10/2018	Methods of Math. Phys.	Heidelberg University, GER	51	$1 \times 1.5 \text{hours}$
04/2016 - 09/2016	General Relativity	Heidelberg University, GER	132	1×1.5 hours

Teaching Assistant

Period	Title	University	Weekly Teaching
10/2016 - 03/2017	Theoretical Physics I	Heidelberg University, GER	1×1.5 hours
04/2015 - 09/2015	Theoretical Physics IV	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5 \mathrm{hours}$
10/2014 - 03/2015	Quantum Field Theory	Heidelberg University, GER	1×1.5 hours
10/2013 - 03/2014	Theoretical Physics III	Heidelberg University, GER	1×1.5 hours
04/2013 - 09/2013	Theoretical Physics II	Heidelberg University, GER	1×1.5 hours
10/2012 - 03/2013	Theoretical Physics I	Heidelberg University, GER	1×1.5 hours

REFERENCES

Prof. Dr. Mirjam Cvetič

POSITION Fay R. and Eugene L. Langberg Professor EMPLOYER Department of Physics and Astronomy

University of Pennsylvania, USA

EMAIL cvetic@physics.upenn.edu

PHONE +i(215)8988153

Prof. Dr. Ron Donagi

POSITION Thomas A. Scott Professor of Mathematics

EMPLOYER Department of Mathematics

University of Pennsylvania, USA

EMAIL donagi@math.upenn.edu

PHONE +1 (215) 898 8465

Prof. Dr. Max Horn

POSITION Professor

EMPLOYER Department of Mathematics

RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, GER

EMAIL horn@mathematik.uni-kl.de

PHONE +49 631 205 2730